Phil: I can't remember what the actual
trigger was that triggered, but I
can describe to you how they were
affected because the sensory stimuli
was so great that the individual
had gone into crisis point, so could
not process input from even the most
familiar staff at that point, really
into sort of fight or flight mode.
And so came, you know, toward staff,
to quite physical, sort of hitting out
and, you know, screaming and shouting,
and also sounding quite, you know,
whimpering almost, whimpering because,
you know, again reached that sort of
state of fight or flight it's, you know,
a very sort of primitive instinct, you
know, and they weren't able to process
verbal or visual support at that point.
Weren't able to verbalise themselves
at that point, what they were feeling,
what they needed to support that.
So first and foremost, just to make sure
that, you know, everybody is safe, the
individual and staff supporting as well.
I always use the analogy of, you know,
on the plane, when they say about
the mask coming down in the event of
needing oxygen masks, if you ever, if
you're supporting a child, make sure
you put your mask on first before the
child so that you can support them.
You've got to make sure everybody's safe.
And that includes staff.
So you're not putting
anyone at further risk.
Giving time and space to be able to
calm down a bit and having access
to, like I said earlier, the sensory,
regulatory tools that are relevant
and appropriate for that individual
whilst, but then timing it so that they
are then able to use those effectively
because if an individual has gone
really into crisis from sensory overload
or, you you know, emotional reasons
or any other trigger, then it's very
difficult to immediately support because
they can't process anything really.
So having that, make sure everybody's
safe and having time and space - giving
the individual time and space to calm,
and then they're better able to access
things that will help to regulate